<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Zach Lendon's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://zachlendon.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zachlendon.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-02-17T00:29:36-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zachlendon.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zach Lendon]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[zach.lendon@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2012 02 16 Up And Blogging With Mao]]></title>
    <link href="http://zachlendon.github.com/blog/2012/02/17/2012-02-16-up-and-blogging-with-mao/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zachlendon.github.com/blog/2012/02/17/2012-02-16-up-and-blogging-with-mao</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been meaning to get back into blogging for a while.  I really enjoy the technologies I get to work with on an almost daily basis - namely iOS, Grails and various mobile frameworks (JQuery Mobile, Backbone.js, underscore.js, etc.), and hopefully I run across a few things that might be of use to some other people.  At least I&#8217;d like to use this blog to help give an outlet to that illusion.  Having a blog also lets me rant about things and have it stored online for an indeterminate amount of time - who doesn&#8217;t like having their words haunt them for years on end?</p>

<p>So with all that being said, I&#8217;ve had a long list of weak excuses why I hadn&#8217;t gotten a blog going, and high on the list was pretty things like</p>

<ul>
<li>Need to figure out where to host it</li>
<li>Need to figure out what software to use</li>
<li>Need to figure out what styling to use</li>
</ul>


<p>Well I&#8217;ve read enough to determine that <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> is the developer&#8217;s <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> (I probably first noted it being used on Matt Gemmell&#8217;s blog, and his post <a href="http://mattgemmell.com/2011/09/12/blogging-with-octopress/">his experiences blogging with Octopress</a>. I also determined <a href="http://github.com">GitHub</a> is as good of a place as any to host one, for starters at least - and works well with Git-hosted <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>.  <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress&#8217;s</a> default theme (which this blog uses) provides good enough styling for a developer-centric blog in my opinion - for the time being at least.</p>

<p>For now I&#8217;m using <a href="http://mouapp.com">Mouapp</a> for my Markdown editor - recommended by <a href="http://zanthrash.com/">@zanthrash</a> - while I thought I liked the idea of <a href="http://danimal.org/blog/2011/07/31/posting-to-octopress-from-marsedit/">posting to Octopress from MarsEdit</a>, I actually like the raw markdown editing better and being able to see the markup in the same window, vs. building html formatted posts.  Plus it isn&#8217;t that hard to create a new post in Mao, save it to my local blog posts folder, and do a rake generate and deploy - and have it pushed to my github pages repo see it live online - immediately.  I&#8217;m sure this will be a process that will scriptable to make it even easier to do with future posts.</p>

<p>If anyone has tips to make the use of these technologies even better going forward please pass them along.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
